<?xml version= "1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Overview</title> 
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <author email="tcolson@cisco.com">Tim Colson</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/struts/menu.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>  

    <section name="Overview"> 

        <p>The VelocityStruts sub-project integrates Velocity with the 
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a> 
        Web application framework and enables the use of velocity templates 
        interchangeably with JSP pages for the view layer.</p>
 
        <p>Various other 
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/powered.html#Frameworks%20that%20support%20Velocity">web application frameworks</a> 
        offer built-in support for Velocity templates. This project 
        provides the minimal glue necessary to give Struts developers 
        an alternative to JSP. </p>
        
        <p><img src="../images/velstruts_diag1.png" border="0"/></p>
        <p><strong>Diagram 1.</strong> Comparison of JSP and Velocity for 
        the view layer in a Struts application.</p> 

        <p>As we follow the typical Struts process flow in Diagram 1, 
        notice how there is relatively little change except for the addition 
        of Velocity. The velocity-struts.jar leverages a standalone Velocity 
        servlet to process template files (specifically, the jar file is 
        velocity-tools-x.x.jar) and uses some drop-in tools to provide 
        transparent access to Struts specific objects (ex. message resources, 
        form beans, errors, links). The action mapping file will simply contain 
        ActionForwards that send control to a Velocity-based View layer instead 
        of sending to a JSP. </p>

        <p>Also notable is that Velocity and JSP are <strong>not</strong> 
        mutually exclusive. Both technologies can be used in the same 
        application without any problems. This allows developers the option 
        of trying Velocity without heavy modification to existing applications.</p>

        <p>We're convinced that once you give Velocity a try, you'll really like it.</p>
    </section>
	
    <section name="Benefits">
        <p>There are many different reasons why people are choosing Velocity 
        technology for the view layer. Here are some:</p>
        <p>
        <ul>
            <li>Velocity helps enforce a clean separation between the view 
            layer and the model/control layers. This leads to clean application 
            design and a clear separation of concerns between View Designers 
            and back-end Developers.</li>

            <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/vtl-reference-guide.html">Velocity Template Language (VTL)</a>
            has few directives and is simple and easy to learn. Most 
            people report being productive within a day.</li>

            <li>Velocity is easy to extend with <i>Tools</i> which are simply 
            any class which has public methods. These are typically easier to 
            develop than JSP custom tag libraries.</li>

            <li>Velocity 'macros' are a powerful tool for the View Designer. 
            They enable the creation of reusable snippets of markup, often 
            eliminating what would have been a need to develop a custom tag 
            library or other server-side tool.</li>

            <li>Velocity templates are <strong>not</strong> limited to HTML 
            and can be used to produce any type of text output including XML, 
            SQL, ASCII, PostScript, etc.</li>

            <li>Velocity enables easy access to dynamic data 
            that Web Designers can understand.</li>

            <li>Velocity being interpreted, enables a simple development cycle 
            where template errors can quickly be localized and debugged.</li>

            <li>Velocity, which caches templates for speed, has been reported 
            to have performance comparable or better than JSP.</li>

            <li>Velocity is <strong>supported</strong> by an active and helpful 
            community of users and developers.</li>
        </ul>
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Success Stories">
        <p>Comments from folks who are using Struts and Velocity:</p>
        <p>
        <blockquote>
          <p>&quot;<i>We've been using Struts/Velocity for some time now and we find it to be
          an extremely well matched combination.  One of the main advantages of
          Velocity is that the syntax is incredibly easy.  I can explain it to a
          designer who has never seen it before and expect them to be useful
          within an hour.</i>&quot; </p>
          <p>&quot;<i>One of the nicest things it enforces is the separation of presentation
          layer and business logic.  It removes the desire to 'fix' problems by
          just putting a small change into the JSP via scriptlets.  It also makes
          the code a <strong>lot</strong> more readable which also reduces the 
          development time.</i>&quot;</p>
          <p>&quot;<i>Struts is a solid framework and Velocity makes it 
          even better.</i>&quot;</p>    
        </blockquote>
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="What About Struts 1.1?">
        <p>Well, since our 1.0 release, we've been <a href="../changes.html">busy</a>.  Thanks in large part to the
        efforts of our newest committer on the project (Marino), we've now
        implemented support for all of the new features in Struts 1.1.  The latest
        nightly builds include support for ActionMessages, Tiles, javascript validation, 
        and modules, among numerous other improvements.</p>
        
        <p>In the meantime, here's a few tips for using Velocity Tools with Struts 1.1:
        
        <ol>
          <li>Tiles alternatives:
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/tools/view/layoutservlet.html">VelocityLayoutServlet</a>
          or the disscusion <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-user@jakarta.apache.org/msg63487.html">here</a></li>
          <li>Wanna use Validator? There's some example code 
          <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/velocity-user@jakarta.apache.org/msg09167.html">here</a></li>
          (though this doesn't demonstrate new client-side validation feature).
        </ol>
        </p>
        
        <p>Hopefully, we'll be able to get a Velocity Tools 1.1 release out the door
        soon. If you're interested in helping us finish it up and test it out, come 
        over to the velocity-dev list and/or checkout the latest code from CVS!</p>
        
        <br clear="all" />
        
    </section>


    <section name="License">
        <p>This software is licensed under the 
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/license.html">Apache Software License</a></p>
    </section>
 </body>

</document>
