<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Velocity View For Struts</title>
    <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
    <author email="geirm@apache.org">Geir Magnusson Jr.</author>
    <projectfile>xdocs/view/menu.xml</projectfile>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Welcome to VelocityServlet">

    <p>VelocityServlet is a subproject of Velocity. Its goals is to create a 
    standalone Velocity servlet that can be used for template rendering 
    in Web applications.</p>
    <p>Intended audience of this subproject are Web
    application developers that plan on adding Velocity as a view layer
    technology to their Servlet-based web application framework. VelocityServlet 
    offers the following key features:</p>
    
    <ul>
        <li>VelocityViewServlet provides is a standalone Java servlet that renders Velocity 
            templates. Its class name is 
            <code>org.apache.velocity.tools.view.servlet.VelocityViewServlet</code>.
            It can be invoked either directly from Web clients or from other servlets
            by forwarding request for template rendering to it. Its usage is
            similar to the JSPServlet for rendering JSP pages.</li>
        <li>VelocityViewServlet makes ServletRequest attributes, HttpSession attributes and 
            ServletContext attributes automatically available to the template designer 
            through the Velocity context. It is not necessary to explicitely
            populate the Velocity context.</li>
        <li>VelocityViewServlet offers toolbox support. It is possible to define a set
            of view tools (view helpers) that are made available to the template
            designer automatically through the Velcity context.</li>
        <li>Velocity log output can be redirected to the log infrastructure 
            of the Web application. By default, the log is directed to the
            logging facility provided by the Servlet API.</li>
    </ul>
       
    <p>Using VelocityViewServlet, it becomes possible to write Web applications that are 
    independent of a particular view technology. This opens a straightforward
    migration path between JSP pages and Velocity templates as the view layer
    technology in Web applications.</p>

    <p>A typical application case for VelocityViewServlet is to use it in conjunction
    with a Servlet-based web application framework. 
    <a href="../../struts/docs/index.html">VelocityStruts</a> is a Velocity
    subproject that brings Velocity to the Struts world and is the first 
    application that takes advantage of VelocityViewServlet.</p>


    <p><strong>To be added</strong></p>
    <ul>
        <li>Examples</li>
        <li>Configuration of Servlet</li>
        <li>Configuration of Toolbox</li>
        <li><a href="../javadoc/index.html">Javadoc</a></li>
    </ul>
  </section>
 
 </body>
</document>

