<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Generic Tools</title>
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/generic/menu.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body> 

    <section name="Overview">

        <p>Generic Tools contain a collection of reusable and well 
        documented tools of general interest..</p>

        <p>Emphasis is being put on providing tool documentation that is 
        suitable for template designers. To achive this goal, a documentation
        format has been defined that captures all information relevant to the
        template designer. It is being supplied in addition to the customary
        Javadoc. This should help to achieve what we always claim for Velocity:
        "Decouple the work of template designers from the work of software
        developers". Look at the Struts <a href="../struts/MessageTool.html">MessageTool</a>
        for a good example of the new documentation format. </p>
        <p>We are interested in Designer and Developer feedback on the format. </p>
        
        <p>Contributions of generic tools are welcome, see <a href="#Contributions">below</a> for more details.</p>
          
        <p><strong>Generic Tools:</strong></p>

        <dl>
            <dt><a href="DateTool.html"><strong>DateTool</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>A tool for manipulating and formating dates.</dd>
                
            <dt><a href="MathTool.html"><strong>MathTool</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>A tool for performing floating point math.</dd>

            <dt><strong>IteratorTool</strong></dt>
            <dd>A convenience tool to use with #foreach loops. It wraps a list
            to let the designer specify a condition to terminate the loop, 
            and reuse the same list in different loops.</dd>

            <dt><strong>RenderTool</strong></dt>
            <dd>A tool to evaluate and render arbitrary strings of VTL (Velocity
            Template Language).</dd>
        </dl>
        <br clear="all" />

    </section>

    <section name="Contributions">
        <p>We welcome your contributions to this library. Please post your offer
        to contribute a tool to the 
        <a href="mailto:velocity-user@jakarta.apache.org">Velocity mailing list</a>.</p>

        <p><strong>Checklist for Contributions</strong></p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/code-standards.html">Velocity coding conventions</a></li>
            <li>JavaDoc included (the more detailed the better)</li>
            <li>Examples included (in JavaDoc or as stand-alone template example)</li>
        </ul>
    </section>

 </body>
</document>
