<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <projectfile>xdocs/project.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>

    <section name="Overview">
        <p>
            A Velocity "tool" is just a POJO (plain old java object) that is
            "useful" in a template and is not meant to be rendered in the
            output.  In other words, a "tool" (in Velocity-speak) is meant
            to be used but not seen themselves (e.g. for formatting dates
            or numbers, url building, etc).
        </p>

        <p>
            The VelocityTools project is, first of all, a collection of such
            useful Java classes, as well as infrastructure to easily,
            automatically and transparently make these tools available to your
            Velocity templates.  Other aims of the project include providing
            easy integration of Velocity into the view-layer of your web
            applications (via the
            <a href="view.tag.html">VelocityViewTag</a>,
            <a href="view.servlet.html">VelocityViewServlet</a>), the
            <a href="maven-velocity-tools-plugin/index.html">Maven plugin</a>
            and integration with Struts 1.x applications.
        </p>

        <p>
            In recognition of these varying aims, the VelocityTools project is
            divided into three parts: <a href="generic.html">GenericTools</a>,
            <a href="view.html">VelocityView</a> and <a href="struts.html">
            VelocityStruts</a>. Each of these parts builds on the previous one
            and has its own JAR distribution.
        </p>

        <subsection name="GenericTools">
            <p>
                <a href="generic.html">GenericTools</a> is the set of classes
                that provide basic infrastructure for using tools in standard
                Java SE Velocity projects, as well as a set of tools for use
                in generic Velocity templates.  Perenial favorites here are
                the DateTool, NumberTool and RenderTool, though there are many
                others available as well.
            </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="VelocityView">
            <p>
                <a href="view.html">VelocityView</a> includes all of the
                <a href="generic.html">GenericTools</a> structure and
                specialized tools for using Velocity in the view layer of web
                applications (Java EE projects). This includes the
                <a href="view.servlet.html">VelocityViewServlet</a> or
                <a href="view.layoutservlet.html">VelocityLayoutServlet</a>
                for processing Velocity template requestsm the
                <a href="view.tag.html">VelocityViewTag</a> for
                embedding Velocity in JSP and a
                <a href="maven-velocity-tools-plugin/index.html">Maven plugin</a>
                to embed JSP tag libraries in Velocity templates.
                Popular tools here are the LinkTool
                and the ParameterTool.
            </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="VelocityStruts">
            <p>
                <a href="struts.html">VelocityStruts</a> includes both
                <a href="view.html">VelocityView</a> and <a href="generic.html">
                GenericTools</a> and adds tools for use in Struts 1.x
                applications.  These tools match the functions of the key
                Struts taglibs and provide access to Struts resources, messages,
                tiles, validation functions and more.
            </p>
        </subsection>

        <p>
            It is worth noting that these tools, being POJOs (though some
            require a little configuration) are generally useful and may be
            used within your java classes or even other template languages,
            though you may need to instantiate and configure them manually (not
            difficult) to do so.  VelocityTools 2 has been designed with this
            in mind.  Ask on the user mailing list if you have questions about
            using VelocityTools without Velocity.
        </p>

    </section>

    <section name="What's new in 2.1">
        <p>
            Velocity Tools 2.1 has the following new features:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>
            A <a href="maven-velocity-tools-plugin/index.html">Maven plugin</a> to allow embedding
            of JSP tag libraries inside Velocity templates.
            </li>
        </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="Why 2.0?">
        <p>
            Those already familiar with VelocityTools 1.x may be curious about
            the goals and motivations behind developing VelocityTools 2.
            In planning and developing the 2.0 release, there were three main
            goals:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                Transparent, on-demand tool instantiation (aka lazy loading
                for tools) - This allows you to have many tools available
                (even ones that are expensive to instantiate), but not waste
                time instantiating or initializing/configuring those you don't
                use for every request.
            </li>

            <li>
                More accessible, reusable infrastructure - This allows easier
                access to tools outside of your templates and provides better
                means to integrate VelocityTools support into other web
                frameworks or even other view technologies
                (e.g. VelocityViewTag).
            </li>

            <li>
                Simpler, more flexible toolbox
                <a href="config.html">configuration</a> - Now you can
                configure via a
                <a href="config.properties.html">properties file</a>,
                <a href="config.java.html">plain java</a>, or really
                whatever you want (though perhaps with a bit more work).  No
                <a href="config-xml.html">XML</a> required anymore; though,
                if you do use it, it's now a lot better than it was.
            </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
            These things could not have been accomplished without rewriting
            most of the core infrastructure and configuration code.  At the
            same time, we wanted to make it easy for people to upgrade from
            the 1.x series.  This led to the decision to aim for complete
            backwards compatibility.  Granted much has been deprecated and
            those who directly used or extended the 1.x infrastructure will
            have to update their code in just a few releases, but for the time
            being they should be able to use 2.0 in their applications with
            few problems. Those who merely used the old toolbox.xml format or
            the old tools directly will be immediately able to take advantage
            of the new infrastructure without even updating their
            configuration, though eventually even the old toolbox.xml format
            may be retired.  Don't cry.  You'll like the
            <a href="config-xml.html">new one</a> better once
            you get to know it!  It can do much more with much less typing.
        </p>

    </section>

    <section name="Subversion Repository">
        <p>
            All VelocityTools project code is maintained in the Subversion
            repository which can be reached in a number of ways. The most
            direct method of accessing the repository is through a
            web browser, but to effectively work on the code, a
            <a href="http://svn.tigris.org/links.html#clients">Subversion
            client</a> is required.
        </p>

        <p>
            Repository:
            <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/velocity/tools/trunk/">
                http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/velocity/tools/trunk/
            </a>
        </p>

    </section>

    <section name="Helping Out">
        <subsection name="Communication">
            <p>
            Feedback about the project, whether positive or gently critical,
            is always helpful to those working on the project.  Such feedback
            may be sent to either the user@velocity.apache.org or
            dev@velocity.apache.org
            <a href="http://velocity.apache.org/contact.html">mailing lists</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
            Another great way to help is to simply participate in conversations
            on the mailing list.  On the user list, you can help answer questions
            that other users have. This frees the developers to focus on
            development more than user support.  On the dev list, you can
            participate in design discussions and release votes to help
            maintain the high quality of the releases and direct the future
            directions of the project.
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Contribution">
            <p>
            Those interested in furthering the development of this
            project have an open invitation to jump in and help out.
            We welcome your contributions!
            Patches can be sent to the mailing list or attached to a
            <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/VELTOOLS">JIRA</a>
            issue.  The <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/velocity/VelocityTools">Wiki</a>
            can also be a good place to discuss and develop ideas.
            </p>
            <p>A few good places to get started include:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Documentation (patches for the site or additions to
                the Wiki)</li>
                <li>Improving the example apps</li>
                <li>Working on unresolved tasks in
                    <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/VELTOOLS">JIRA</a></li>
                <li>Contributing to the
                    <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/velocity/VelocimacroLibrary">VelocimacroLibrary</a></li>
            </ul>
            <p>
            Other project goals and proposals can be found in the project
            <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/velocity/tools/trunk/STATUS?view=markup">STATUS</a> file.
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Code">
            <p>
            When contributing code, it helps <strong>immensely</strong> if you follow
            through with the things on this checklist, especially the coding conventions.
            Keeping our code style consistent, our codebase stays easy to read and easy
            to patch.  Adding javadoc (and examples therein) simplifies the documentation
            process and reduces confusion about the purpose of various methods and classes.
            Tests make sure that things work as expected, especially as development continues
            down the road.  Of course, contributions that don't follow the checklist will
            be considered and often accepted, but you can expect the project committers
            to be slower and less enthusiastic in doing so. :)
            </p>
            <p><b>Checklist for Code Contributions</b>:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://wiki.apache.org/velocity/CodeStandards">Velocity coding conventions</a></li>
                <li>Javadoc included (the more detailed the better)</li>
                <li>Examples included (in JavaDoc or as stand-alone template example)</li>
                <li>Tests included (not required but <b>GREATLY</b> appreciated)</li>
            </ul>
        </subsection>

    </section>

    </body>

</document>
