<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2003-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

  $Id: changes.xml,v 1.18 2004/02/21 20:54:19 nbubna Exp $
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Velocity Tools Changes</title>
    <author email="nathan@esha.com">Nathan Bubna</author>
    <projectfile>xdocs/menu.xml</projectfile>
  </properties>
<body>
  <section name="Velocity Tools Changes">
    <p>This document tracks the changes in Velocity Tools between releases.</p>

    <subsection name="1.1-rc1">
      <p>This section describes changes after the 1.1-beta release.</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Changed recommended keys for MessageTool and ActionMessagesTool to $text and $messages. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Changed XMLToolboxManager to use thread context classloader when digesting toolbox. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Fixed session tool initialization/synchronization issue. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added TilesTool methods to import attributes to specific scopes (page/request/session/application). (maj)</li>
      <li>Added new demos for using ValidatorTool, TilesTool, and SecureLinkTool to VelocityStruts example app. (maj)</li>
      <li>Upgraded/refactored MathTool to add floor() and ceil(), make type-handling more intuitive and flexible, and improve number parsing. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Improved resource bundle support in ActionMessagesTool. (ndb)</li>
      <li>ErrorsTool now extends ActionMessagesTool. (ndb)</li>
      <li>LinkTool now encodes URLs using the response's character encoding. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Removed inadvertant JDK 1.4 dependencies from ImportSupport. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Made XMLToolboxManager not abstract (#24840). (ndb)</li>
      <li>De-staticized non-private methods in RenderTool and LinkTool. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added NumberTool for formatting numbers (contributed by Mike Kienenberger). (ndb)</li>
      <li>Filled out and cleaned up DateTool's toDate(...) methods. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Changed VelocityViewServlet's error method to print the stack trace of the root cause when it encounters a MethodInvocationException. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added importAttributes() method to TilesTool to automatically put all attributes of the current Tiles context into the Velocity context. (maj)</li>
      <li>Replaced TilesTool's getString(String) method with getAttribute(String) in order to support "put lists." (maj)</li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="1.1-beta1">
      <p>This section describes changes after the 1.0 release.</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Made VelocityViewServlet use response.getOutputStream() if response.getWriter() fails.  This is functionality is deprecated and provided as a migration path from 1.0 behavior. (dlr, ndb)</li>
      <li>De-staticized MathTool to make it extendable. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Factored common functionality of ErrorsTool, MessageTool, and ActionMessagesTool into abstract MessageResourcesTool. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added ImportTool as a simple ImportSupport-based tool. (maj)</li>
      <li>Converted TilesTool to extend ImportSupport. This allows easy mixing of view technologies (JSP, Velocity, etc.) in VelocityStruts applications. (thanks go to Matthew Payne for the idea!) (maj)</li>
      <li>Added ImportSupport class for building tools that can import resources from local or remote URLS. (maj)</li>
      <li>Overhauled DateTool to make it more extendable, user-friendly, and add support for standard, localized date-time styles (see DateTool javadoc for more). (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added support for specifying message resource bundles to StrutsUtils, ErrorsTool, ActionMessagesTool, and MessageTool. (maj,ndb)</li>
      <li>Added commons-validator (1.0.2) and sslext jars to library. (maj)</li>
      <li>Added SecureLinkTool for using Struts SSL Extension with VelocityStruts. (maj)</li>
      <li>Added ValidatorTool to provide Struts 1.1 javascript validation for VelocityStruts. (maj)</li>
      <li>output.encoding property (if non-default) is appended to default content-type as the charset. (ndb)</li>
      <li>VelocityViewServlet now uses response.getWriter() instead of response.getOutputStream() as suggested by Matthew Payne. (ndb)</li>
      <li>Improved VelocityViewServlet error handling (exceptions are logged and error() is now more robust). (ndb)</li>
      <li>Put VelocityViewServlet's requestCleanup() call in a 'finally' clause to allow clean after errors during a request. (dlr)</li>
      <li>Fixed miscellaneous javadoc and doc typos (many of which were reported by Takayoshi Kimura) (ndb)</li>
      <li>Allow system to reclaim objects held by pooled writers in VelocityViewServlet (see bug 18951) (ndb)</li>
      <li>Changed LinkTool to automatically check for XHTML setting (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added support for standard XHTML mode setting via toolbox config (ndb)</li>
      <li>Moved request/response/session/application keys to ViewContext and add getAttribute() method (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added selectModule() and getForwardURL() to StrutsUtils (maj)</li>
      <li>Convert VelocityStruts tools to use new StrutsUtils methods and be module aware (maj)</li>
      <li>Removed unused imports from StrutsLinkTool (ndb)</li>
      <li>Refactor StrutsUtils to use Struts 1.1 classes and support modules (maj)</li>
      <li>Added TilesTool (maj)</li>
      <li>Allow subclasses of VelocityViewServlet to use different ToolboxManager implementations (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added CookieTool (contributed by Dmitri Colebatch) (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added demo of &lt;data&gt; elements to simple VelocityView example (ndb)</li>
      <li>Made simple VelocityStruts example catch Commons-Logging output with LogSystemCommonsLog (ndb)</li>
      <li>Convert toolbox setup to use Digester instead of dom4j (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added LogSystemCommonsLog and CommonsLogLogSystem to provide bridges between Commons-Logging and Velocity's LogSystem (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added Commons Logging 1.0.3 jar (ndb)</li>
      <li>Added ActionMessagesTool (ndb)</li>
      <li>Upgrade deprecated Struts 1.0 uses in examples (ndb)</li>
      <li>Updated jars to Struts 1.1, BeanUtils 1.6.1, Digester 1.5, Collections 2.1 (ndb)</li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="1.0">
      <ul>
      <li>Initial release.</li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
