<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Tools Sub-Project</title>
        <author email="geirm@apache.org">Geir Magnusson Jr.</author>
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/menu.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>
    <section name="Overview">
        <p>
        Velocity Tools is a collection of Velocity sub-projects with a common goal
        of creating tools and infrastructure for building both web and non-web
        applications using the Velocity template engine.
        </p>

        <subsection name="VelocityView" >
            <p><a href="view/">VelocityView</a>
            contains a standalone servlet (VelocityViewServlet) which can render 
            templates for web applications. </p>
            <p> Also included is a Toolbox Manager which can automatically make 
            &quot;view tools&quot; and data available to the templates. Any class 
            with public methods can be used as a tool in the template.
            </p>
            <p>
            <a href="view/layoutservlet.html">VelocityLayoutServlet</a> is an 
            extension of the basic VelocityViewServlet that can render screen 
            content into common layout templates.</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Generic Tools" >
            <p><a href="generic/">Generic Tools</a> is a group of reuseable and 
            documented tools that can be added to a Velocity context. A 
            <b>tool</b> is simply a class which can perform various tasks when 
            made available to the Velocity engine. Most tools are optimized for use
            with an automatically managed toolbox (see VelocityViewServlet).</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="VelocityStruts" >
            <p><a href="struts/">VelocityStruts</a> is a set of tools for using the 
            Velocity template engine as the view layer for a web application built upon the
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a> framework.</p>
            <p>This work leverages the <strong>VelocityViewServlet</strong> and 
            additional tools which make it easy to integrate the Velocity with 
            Struts. Several example hybrid applications are included.</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Example Applications">
            <p>Several example applications are currently available, including
            one to demonstrate the use of Velocity as a view technology for Struts. 
            The example utilizes both Velocity and JSP files for the view in parallel 
            so that they can be compared easily. Also, resources bundle usage for 
            language localization is demonstrated there. Other examples include a demonstration
            of the use of the VelocityLayoutServlet and a minimal "simple" application.</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>
    </section>    

    <section name="Download">
        <p><strong>Releases</strong></p>
        <p>
          Velocity Tools 1.0 has been released and is available 
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity-tools/">here</a>.
        </p>

        <p><strong>Source Code</strong></p>
        <p>
          Nightly snapshots of the project source are available as binaries
          <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/nightly/">here</a>.
        </p>
        <br clear="all"/>
    </section>

    <section name="CVS Repository">
        <p>All Velocity Tools project code is maintained in the 
        CVS repository <b>jakarta-velocity-tools</b>.</p>

        <p>Web Browser: <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/">
        http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/</a></p>

        <p>CVS Client: <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html">http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html</a>.
        </p>
        <br clear="all"/>
    </section>

    <section name="Wanna help?">
        <p>This project is still young and has a growing user base.  With the publicity 
        of this first release, we expect the growth to increase significantly.
        We would like to encourage interested developers to evaluate the project
        and send feedback to the velocity-user or velocity-dev mailing list.</p>
        <p>Those interested in furthering the development of this project are
        especially welcome to jump in and help out.  Patches can be sent to the 
        mailing list or attached to a
        <a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/enter_bug.cgi?product=Velocity&amp;component=Tools">bugzilla</a>
        ticket.  The <a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/wiki/apachewiki.cgi?VelocityTools">Wiki</a>
        can also be a good place to discuss and develop ideas.</p>

        <p>A few good places to get started include:
          <ul>
            <li>Documentation (patches for the site or additions to the Wiki)</li>
            <li>Improving the example apps</li>
            <li>Contributing to the <a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/wiki/apachewiki.cgi?VelocimacroLibraries">VelocimacroLibraries</a></li>
          </ul>
        Other project goals and proposals can be found in the project 
        <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/STATUS">STATUS</a>
        file.</p>
    </section>
 </body>

</document>