<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Velocity Tools Project</title>
        <author email="geirm@apache.org">Geir Magnusson Jr.</author>
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/menue.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>

    <section name="Welcome to the Velocity Tools Project">

        <p>
        Velocity Tools is a subproject of Velocity. It is the umbrella project for 
        several Velocity subprojects that have the goal to create tools and infrastructure
        useful for creating applications using the Velocity template engine. 
        </p>

        <p><strong>Subprojects</strong></p>

        <dl>
            <dt><strong><a href="vellibrary.html">VelocityLibrary</a></strong></dt> 
            <dd>VelocityLibrary is an effort to setup a library of reuseable and well documented
                context tools. Most tools are optimized for use with an automatically managed
                toolbox (see VelocityServlet).</dd>

            <dt><strong><a href="../struts/docs/index.html">VelocityStruts</a></strong></dt>
            <dd>The VelocityStruts package is a set of context tools, examples and documentation for 
                using the Velocity template engine as a view layer technology for the 
                <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a> web 
                application framework. It is based on the VelocityServlet project.</dd> 

            <dt><strong><a href="../view/docs/velservlet.html">VelocityServlet</a></strong></dt>
            <dd>VelocityServlet is a standalone servlet that can be used for template 
                rendering in Web applications. It offers automatic population of the 
                Velocity context and automatic, configurable management of context tools. 
                Other efforts within this project are the development of a toolbox manager
                and the definition of a set of interfaces for context tools, thereby enabling the
                efficient handling and reuse of context tools.</dd>

            <dt><strong>Utilities</strong></dt> 
            <dd>When in place, this will be a library of Velocity-related utilities.</dd>
    
            <dt><strong>Velocimacros</strong></dt> 
            <dd>When in place, this will be a repository of Velocimacros for use in 
            Velocity templates.</dd>
        </dl>
    </section>

    <section name="CVS Repository">

        <p>
        The code for all the efforts within the Velocity Tools project is maintained
        in the CVS repository jakarta-velocity-tools. It is available via:</p>
        
        <p>Web Browser: <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/">
        http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/</a></p> 
        
        <p>CVS Client: <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html</a>.
        </p>

        <p>Since Velocity Tools is an umbrella project for several subprojects, look for
        status information, releases, documentation and application examples within 
        the subprojects.</p>

    </section>

 </body>
</document>

