<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Tools Sub-Project</title>
        <author email="geirm@apache.org">Geir Magnusson Jr.</author>
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/menu.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>
    <section name="Overview">
        <p>
        Velocity Tools is a collection of Velocity sub-projects with a common goal
        of creating tools and infrastructure for building both web and non-web
        applications using the Velocity template engine.
        </p>
        <p>Status information, releases, documentation and application examples 
        will generally be located within the individual sub-projects.</p>

        <subsection name="VelocityView" >
            <p><a href="view/">VelocityView</a>
            contains a standalone servlet (VelocityViewServlet) which can render 
            templates for web applications. </p>
            <p> Also included is a Toolbox Manager which can automatically make 
            &quot;view tools&quot; and data available to the templates. Any class 
            with public methods can be used as a tool in the template.
            </p>
            <p>
            <a href="view/layoutservlet.html">VelocityLayoutServlet</a> is an 
            extension of the basic VelocityViewServlet that can render screen 
            content into common layout templates.</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Generic Tools" >
            <p><a href="generic/">Generic Tools</a> is a group of reuseable and 
            documented tools that can be added to a Velocity context. A 
            <b>tool</b> is simply a class which can perform various tasks when 
            made available to the Velocity engine. Most tools are optimized for use
            with an automatically managed toolbox (see VelocityViewServlet).</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="VelocityStruts" >
            <p><a href="struts/">VelocityStruts</a> is a set of tools for using the 
            Velocity template engine as the view layer for a web application built upon the
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a> framework.</p>
            <p>This work leverages the <strong>VelocityViewServlet</strong> and 
            additional tools which make it easy to integrate the Velocity with 
            Struts. Several example hybrid applications are included.</p>
            <br clear="all" />
        </subsection>

     </section>

    <section name="CVS Repository">
        <p>All Velocity Tools project code is maintained in the 
        CVS repository <b>jakarta-velocity-tools</b>.</p>

        <p>Web Browser: <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/">
        http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/</a></p>

        <p>CVS Client: <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html</a>.
        </p>
    </section>
 </body>

</document>