<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/menu.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>

    <section name="Welcome to the VelocityStruts Project">

        <p>VelocityStruts is a subproject of Velocity that aims to integrate Velocity
        with the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a> Web application framework.</p>

        <p>Struts is one of a growing number of <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/powered.html#Frameworks%20that%20support%20Velocity">web application frameworks</a> that offer Velocity as a view layer technology. The integration with Struts offers now to Struts developers an alternative to JSP, the default view technology supported by Struts.</p>

        <p>There are many different reasons why people are choosing to use Velocity as their view layer technology. The main advantages of Velocity compared to other view technologies are:</p>
        
        <ul>
            <li>Velocity enforces a clear separation of the view aspects of an application from the model and control aspects. This leads to clean application designs and a clear separation of the work of view designers and server developers.</li>
            <li>The <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/vtl-reference-guide.html">Velocity Template Language</a> (VTL) is a simple and easy to learn scripting language. With less than ten language directives, most people are up and running within a day.</li>
            <li>Velocity is easy to extend with so called <i>View Tools</i>. View tools are easier to develop than customer tag libraries in JSP. Any class with public methods can serve as a view tool.</li>
            <li>Velocity really shines when it comes to access to application data from within the templates. It handles access to objects and their methods very much like in scripting languages such as JavaScript and will feel familiar to template designers.</li>
            <li>Velocity is an interpreted language. This leads to a simple development cycle. Template error can easily be localized and debugged.</li>
            <li>Many users of Velocity have reported that the performance of Velocity is comparable if not sligthly better than JSP.</li>
            <li>Last but not least, Velocity is backed by a very active and supportive community of users and developers.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>Velocity's capabilities reach well beyond the realm of web sites; it can generate SQL and PostScript and XML from templates. It can be used either as a standalone utility for generating source code and reports, or as an integrated component of other systems. To find out more about Velocity, please consult the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity">Velocity Home Page</a>.</p>

        <p>This is a work in progress. Frequent updates are expected. Please consult the  <a href="#Download">Download section</a> for the current status of the project.</p>

    </section>


    
    <section name="Documentation">

        <p>To get started using Velocity for Strust applications, we recommend that you first read this document. It gives an overview of the available documentation and points you to examples and the downloadable software.</p>
        
        <p>If you are new to Velocity, it will be helpful to become somewhat familiar with Velocity before you continue:</p>
        
        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">Velocity Home Page</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/user-guide.html">Velocity User Guide</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/vtl-reference-guide.html">Velocity Template Language Reference Guide</a></li>
        </ul>

        <p>To start working with Velocity and Struts we recommend that you download and try out the examples, browse the user's guide and the reference documentation.</p>
        
        <ul>
            <li><a href="#">Examples</a></li>
            <li><a href="userguide.html">Velocity for Struts User's Guide</a></li>
            <li><a href="struts-index.html">Velocity for Struts Reference Documentation</a></li>
        </ul>

        <p>If this documentation does not answer all your questions, we would like to hear back from you. Post your question to the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">Velocity users' mailing list</a>.</p>        
    </section>


    <section name="Download">
        <p>Velocity for Struts is currently in a pre-release phase. A release will be made as soon as the API is mature, the software stable and the documentation complete. Available for download is the
        current source from the CVS repository.</p>

        <p><strong>Source Code</strong></p>
        <p>The source can be accessed with <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/">ViewCVS</a> or your favorite CVS client. See <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">Jakarta CVS Repositories</a> for instructions. The name of the repository is <code>jakarta-velocity-tools</code>. Look for the README files that come with the downloaded source.</p>


        <p><strong>Example Application</strong></p>
        <p>We have compiled several small example applications that demonstrate the use of Velocity as a view technology for Struts. These examples are included in the source repository. See file struts/README in the source for instructions on how to build and deploy the examples. It's pretty easy. There is an ant script that does everything for you. These examples can serve as the starting point for your own experiments with Velocity for Struts.</p>
        

        <p>We would like to encourage interested developers to try and evaluate the software and give us feedback.</p>

    </section>


    <section name="License">
    
        <p>This software is licensed under the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/license.html">Apache Software License</a></p>
    
    </section>
 </body>
</document>

