<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Project VelLibrary</title>
        <author email="sidler@apache.org">Gabriel Sidler</author>
        <projectfile>xdocs/vellibrary-menue.xml</projectfile>
    </properties>

    <body>

    <section name="Welcome to the VelLibrary Project">

        <p>VelLibrary is a Velocity subproject that aims to build of collection
        of reusable and well documented context tools.</p>

        <p>Emphasis is being put on providing tool documentation that is 
        suitable for template designers. To achive this goal, a documenation
        format has been defined that captures all information relevant to the
        template designer. It is being supplied in addition to the customary
        Javadoc. This should help to achive what we always claim for Velocity:
        "Decouple the work of template designers from the work of software
        developers". Look at the <a href="../struts/docs/MessageTool.html">Struts MessageTool</a> for a good example of the
        new documentation format. We are keen on your feedback. </p>
        
        <p>Your contribution of useful context tools to the VelLibrary
        project are welcome. See <a href="#Contributions">below</a> for more details.</p>
        
        <p><strong>VelLibrary Content:</strong></p>

        <dl>
            <dt><a href="../tools/docs/DateTool.html"><strong>DateTool</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>A tool for manipulating and formating dates.</dd>
                
            <dt><a href="../tools/docs/MathTool.html"><strong>MathTool</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>A tool for performing floating point math.</dd>
                
            <dt><a href="../tools/docs/ParameterParser.html"><strong>ParameterParser</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>A tool for easy parsing of servlet request parameters.</dd>
                
            <dt><a href="../struts/docs/tools.html"><strong>StrutsTools</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>This includes four tools that integrate Velocity with
            Struts. Velocity is now a real alternative view layer technology
            for Struts applications.</dd>
                
            <dt><a href="../tools/docs/ToolLoader.html"><strong>ToolLoader</strong></a></dt>
            <dd>A tool allowing template designers to load context tools 
            from within the template.</dd>
        </dl>

    </section>


    <section name="Download">

        <p>The is no release available at this point in time.</p>
        
        <pre> </pre>


    </section>


    <section name="Contributions">

        <p>We welcome your contributions to this library. Please post your offer
        to contribute a tool to the 
        <a href="mailto:velocity-user@jakarta.apache.org">Velocity mailing list</a>.</p>

        <p><strong>Checklist for Contributions</strong></p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/code-standards.html">Velocity coding conventions</a></li>
            <li>JavaDoc included (the more detailed the better)</li>
            <li>Examples included (in JavaDoc or as stand-alone template example)</li>
        </ul>
        
                        
    </section>


 </body>
</document>

