<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <projectfile>xdocs/project.xml</projectfile>
    <subprojectfile>xdocs/view.project.xml</subprojectfile>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Overview">
    <p>VelocityView provides support for rapidly and cleanly building web applications
    using Velocity templates in the view layer.  The project is designed with the
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/further-reading/pullmodel.html">Pull-MVC Model</a>
    in mind and works well in conjunction with web application frameworks that act
    as the controller (e.g. <a href="../struts/index.html">Struts</a>), but can be used
    quite effectively on its own for those creating simpler applications.
    </p>
    <p>Key features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><b><a href="javadoc/org/apache/velocity/tools/view/servlet/VelocityViewServlet.html">VelocityViewServlet</a>
          class</b> - standalone servlet that renders Velocity
          templates. Invoked directly from web clients requests, or via servlet
          forwarding similar to how JSP files are rendered by JSPServlet.</li>
      <li>The HttpServletRequest, HttpSession, ServletContext,
          and their attributes are automatically available in your templates.</li>
      <li>Tools can also be made available to your templates, through a
          <strong>toolbox</strong> configuration file.</li>
      <li>A number of useful, extendable tools for developing web applications are
          already provided for your convenience.</li>
      <li>Logging can be directed to the log infrastructure of the Web application.
          (default is the logging facility provided by the Servlet API).</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Using VelocityViewServlet, it becomes possible to write web applications that
    are independent of a particular view technology. This opens a straightforward
    migration path between JSP pages and Velocity templates as the view layer
    technology in web applications.</p>

    <p>A typical application use-case is to provide the view rendering layer for
    a servlet-based web application framework. The
    <a href="../struts/">VelocityStruts</a> subproject
    uses the approach to bring Velocity templates to the Struts application framework.</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Installation">
    <p>The VelocityViewServlet needs to be installed into your servlet container
    so it can handle all request for *.vm (velocity template) files. There are
    only two additional configuration files, and they are shown in
    detail below.</p>

    <br clear="all" />

    <subsection name="Servlet Setup">
      <p>The servlet configuration (<strong>web.xml</strong>) must be
      modified to include a reference to the VelocityViewServlet
      (or subclass thereof) which will perform the rendering. All *.vm files are
      mapped to this servlet which will populate the 'context' with
      Request, Session, and Application scopes plus any additional tools
      specified in the <strong>toolbox.xml</strong> file. The servlet
      will use this contextual information and the Velocity Engine to
      render the template file. </p>
      <br clear="all" />
      <p><strong>Note:</strong> Additional functionality can be achieved
      through subclassing the VelocityViewServlet, and will be discussed further in
      the VelocityLayoutServlet below. </p>

      <p><b>web.xml</b></p>
      <sourcecode>&lt;!-- Define Velocity template compiler --&gt;
&lt;servlet&gt;
  &lt;servlet-name&gt;velocity&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
  &lt;servlet-class&gt;
    org.apache.velocity.tools.view.servlet.VelocityViewServlet
  &lt;/servlet-class&gt;

  &lt;!-- 
    Unless you plan to put your toolbox.xml and velocity.properties
    under different folders or give them different names, then these
    two init-params are unnecessary as of VelocityTools 1.3.  The
    VelocityViewServlet will automatically look for these files in
    the following locations.
  --&gt;
  &lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;org.apache.velocity.toolbox&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;/WEB-INF/toolbox.xml&lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/init-param&gt;

  &lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;org.apache.velocity.properties&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;/WEB-INF/velocity.properties&lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/init-param&gt;
&lt;/servlet&gt;

&lt;!-- Map *.vm files to Velocity --&gt;
&lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
  &lt;servlet-name&gt;velocity&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
  &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.vm&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
&lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;</sourcecode>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Velocity Configuration">
      <p>Velocity configuration is <strong>optional</strong>, and for
      most applications the defaults will work fine. The
      <strong>velocity.properties</strong> file contains settings that
      affect logging, encoding, and macro settings.</p>
      <p>The default configuration specifies the location of a 'global'
      Velocimacro template. This file can contain macros which will be
      made available to all templates.</p>

      <p>The location of the configuration file may be specified in web.xml,
      but it is recommended the file be placed inside the hidden WEB-INF
      directory of the web application and named 'velocity.properties' which
      is where the VelocityViewServlet will look for it in the absence of
      any location specified in the web.xml.
      An example configuration file is included with the distribution.</p>
      <p>Please see the
      <a href="http://velocity.apache.org/engine/devel/user-guide.html">Velocity User's Guide</a>
      for more information on Velocity configuration.</p>

      <sourcecode>  velocimacro.library = /WEB-INF/VM_global_library.vm
  velocimacro.permissions.allow.inline = true
  velocimacro.permissions.allow.inline.to.replace.global = false
  velocimacro.permissions.allow.inline.local.scope = false
  velocimacro.context.localscope = false</sourcecode>

      <br clear="all"/>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Toolbox Configuration">
      <p>The toolbox file, <strong>WEB-INF/toolbox.xml</strong> by
      default, maps names of our choosing to the classes that they will
      represent. It's easier than that sounds.</p>
      <p>Think about asking our friend Jon to grab us a 'wrench' from a
      real toolbox. Jon just needs to know which wrench we want (metric,
      pipe, crescent etc,). He doesn't need to know what the wrench does
      nor what we are planning to do with it.</p>
      <p>The Velocity Toolbox works the same way, we must only specify
      which tool to assign to a name, and then the Velocity engine takes
      care of the rest by making any public method available to the
      template. For example, from the definitions below, the template
      could call $wrench.getSize() or $wrench.size .</p>

      <p><b>PipeWrench.java</b></p>
      <sourcecode>public class PipeWrench {
  public String getSize() {
	return "Large Pipe Wrench!";
  }
} </sourcecode>

      <p><b>toolbox.xml</b></p>
      <sourcecode>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;toolbox&gt;
  &lt;tool&gt;
     &lt;key&gt;wrench&lt;/key&gt;
     &lt;scope&gt;application&lt;/scope&gt;
     &lt;class&gt;PipeWrench&lt;/class&gt;
  &lt;/tool&gt;
&lt;/toolbox&gt;</sourcecode>

      <br clear="all"/>

      <p><b>Tool Scopes</b></p>

      <p>The toolbox support built into the VelocityViewServlet also provides
      support for specifying the scope of your tool with regards to the
      servlet environment.  Tools may be placed within the <i>request</i>,
      <i>session</i>, or <i>application</i> scopes of your web app.</p>
      <p>The scope that you set for your tool will determine both its
      lifecycle and, if the tool has a <code>public init(Object)</code> method,
      then the scope will also determine what data is passed to that method:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><i>application</i> scoped tools will be instantiated only once and then
        reused for each request.  Due to this, it is <em>strongly</em> encouraged
        that your application scoped tools be completely threadsafe.  The MathTool
        in the <a href="../generic/">GenericTools</a> section is a good example of tool meant to be application
        scoped.  If an application scoped tool implements ViewTool, then the
        javax.servlet.ServletContext for the webapp will be passed to its
        <code>init(Object)</code> method after it is instantiated.</li>

        <li><i>session</i> scoped tools are instantiated once per unique session and
        are then reused for every request associated with that particular session. If
        a session scoped tool implements ViewTool, then its <code>init(Object)</code>
        method will be passed the
        <a href="javadoc/org/apache/velocity/tools/view/context/ViewContext.html">ViewContext</a>
        of the request during which the session was created.</li>

        <li><i>request</i> is the default scope.  If no scope is specified for a
        &lt;tool&gt; in your toolbox.xml, then it will be automatically set as
        <i>request</i> scope.  Tools with this scope are instantiated for every
        servlet request fed to the VelocityViewServlet.  If a request scoped tool
        implements ViewTool, then its <code>init(Object)</code> method will be
        passed the current ViewContext.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>You can specify the scope of your tools by adding a &lt;scope&gt;
      element to your toolbox.xml entries like this:</p>

      <sourcecode>&lt;tool&gt;
   &lt;key&gt;math&lt;/key&gt;
   &lt;scope&gt;application&lt;/scope&gt;
   &lt;class&gt;org.apache.velocity.tools.generic.MathTool&lt;/class&gt;
&lt;/tool&gt;</sourcecode>

      <br clear="all"/>

      <p><b>Tool Request Paths</b></p>

      <p>You can specify a restriction on the request URIs for which the tool
      will be put in the context using the &lt;request-path&gt; element.
      It can be an exact request path (matching one page) or end with the
      <code>*</code> wildard, meaning that incoming request paths need only
      start with the provided value for the tool to be available in the context.
      For instance:</p>

      <sourcecode>&lt;tool&gt;
   &lt;key&gt;catalog&lt;/key&gt;
   &lt;scope&gt;request&lt;/scope&gt;
   &lt;request-path&gt;/catalog/*&lt;/request-path&gt;
   &lt;class&gt;com.mycompany.tools.CatalogTool&lt;/class&gt;
&lt;/tool&gt;</sourcecode>

      <p>For now, this request-path filter is only valid for request scoped tools.
      In VelocityTools 2.0, we plan to support this for session and application
      scoped tools as well.</p>

      <br clear="all"/>

      <p><b>Tool Parameters</b></p>

      <p>The toolbox support built into the VelocityViewServlet also provides
      support for passing configuration parameters to tools that have a
      <code>public void configure(java.util.Map params)</code> method.
      This method will only be called if parameters have been specified for the tool.</p>

      <p>You can specify parameters for your tools by adding a &lt;parameter&gt;
      element to your toolbox.xml entries like this:</p>

      <sourcecode>&lt;tool&gt;
   &lt;key&gt;math&lt;/key&gt;
   &lt;scope&gt;application&lt;/scope&gt;
   &lt;class&gt;com.foo.tools.MyTool&lt;/class&gt;
   &lt;parameter name="my.parameter.name" value="my.parameter.value"/&gt;
&lt;/tool&gt;</sourcecode>

      <br clear="all"/>

      <p><b>Toolbox Data</b></p>

      <p>In addition to specifiying arbitrary Java classes as <b>tools</b>
      to be automatically available to your templates, the toolbox support
      also includes the ability to specify arbitrary strings, booleans, and
      numbers to be automatically available in your templates.  The format
      is as follows:</p>

      <sourcecode>&lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot;?&gt;
&lt;toolbox&gt;
  &lt;data type=&quot;number&quot;&gt;
     &lt;key&gt;app_version&lt;/key&gt;
     &lt;value&gt;0.9&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data type=&quot;string&quot;&gt;
     &lt;key&gt;app_name&lt;/key&gt;
     &lt;value&gt;Jon's Tool Shop&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
  &lt;data type=&quot;boolean&quot;&gt;
     &lt;key&gt;debug&lt;/key&gt;
     &lt;value&gt;true&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;
&lt;/toolbox&gt;</sourcecode>

    <p>As with your tools, your data will be exposed to your templates
    under the specified key (e.g. $app_version, $app_name, $debug).</p>

    <br clear="all" />

    </subsection>
  </section>

  <section name="VelocityLayoutServlet">
    <p>One derivative of the VelocityViewServlet is the
    <a href="layoutservlet.html"><strong>VelocityLayoutServlet</strong></a>.
    This servlet performs a simplified 'two-pass render' in order to apply a
    shared, common layout to all of the web pages in an application.</p>

    <p>The Struts &quot;template&quot; tag library does something similar,
    but requires a separate file to define which 'layout' file to use and
    which .jsp files to render into that layout. The VelocityLayoutServlet
    takes a simpler approach. It first renders the primary template being
    called (example: showDetails.vm) into a content holder variable
    (ex. $screen_content). Next, the servlet loads a 'layout' file. It
    uses the existing data, including any additional variables set or
    changed by the first template, to render a the layout template.</p>

    <p>The VelocityLayoutServlet also allows you to specify an 'error'
    template to be displayed when an exception is thrown during the
    processing of a requested template.  This allows you to provide
    a customized error screen for a more user-friendly application.</p>

    <p>Detailed documentation here: <a href="layoutservlet.html">VelocityLayoutServlet</a>.</p>
    <br clear="all" />
  </section>

  <section name="Examples">
    <p>A simple application example has been included to demonstrate the use
    of the VelocityViewServlet with automatically loaded view tools.</p>

    <p>To run the examples you need Tomcat 4.x, Tomcat 5.0.x, Tomcat 5.5.x,
     or a compatible servlet runner.</p>

    <p>The build process automatically generates a ready-to-deploy <b>simple.war</b>
    archive file located in the examples subdirectory. Deploy (i.e. copy) this
    simple.war file  to the webapps directory of your servlet runner and restart.
    Now point a web browser at the following url:</p>


    <p><b>http://&lt;your_server&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/simple/</b></p>
    <br clear="all" />
  </section>

  <section name="Known Issues">
  	<p>
      Since Tomcat 5.5 is using commons-logging as a complete
      logging facility, we are no longer able to direct commons-logging
      output to the servlet log by default.  The result of this is that
      our example apps can no longer contain a commons-logging.properties
      on the classpath if we want them to work with all servlet engines.  
    </p>
    <p>
      When using Tomcat 5.5+, this means that log messages
      from our tools and tool management code are by default sent to the Tomcat
      console, rather than the servlet log.  Velocity Engine and VelocityViewServlet
      messages will still be sent to the servlet log by default. 
      When using other servlet engines or earlier Tomcat versions
      (e.g. Jetty or Tomcat 4.x), you must now add a commons-logging.properties
      file at the root of the classpath that contains:
      <code>
      org.apache.commons.logging.Log=org.apache.velocity.tools.generic.log.LogSystemCommonsLog
      </code>
      if you wish to have tool and tool management log output sent to the
      servlet log.  If you are using Tomcat 5.5+, do NOT do that, as it will
      cause an infinite loop.
    </p>
    <p>
      We plan to resolve this in future versions by removing commons-logging
      from our code in favor of the much improved log wrappers in Velocity Engine 1.5.
      In the meantime, commons-logging remains the most flexible solution.
    </p>
    <br clear="all"/>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
